I am a conductor,
انا مؤلف موسيقي "مايسترو"
and I'm here today
و انا هنا اليوم
to talk to you about trust.
لاتكلم عن الثقة
My job depends upon it.
عملي يعتمد عليها
There has to be, between me and the orchestra,
يجب ان يكون بيني و بين الاوركسترا
an unshakable bond of trust,
اواصر ثقة لا تهتز
born out of mutual respect,
نابعة من الاحترام المتبادل
through which we can spin a musical narrative
و التي من خلالها نستطيع ان ننتج مقطوعة موسيقية
that we all believe in.
نتفق عليها جميعا
Now in the old days, conducting, music making,
و قديما، فان قيادة الفرقة الموسيقية و التاليف الموسيقي
was less about trust and more, frankly, about coercion.
لم يكن يعتمد على الثقة بشكل كبير، بل في حقيقة الامر على الاكراه
Up to and around about the Second World War,
حتى الحرب العالمية الثانية
conductors were invariably dictators --
كان المايستروهات اجمالا دكتاتوريين
these tyrannical figures
هؤلاء الشخصيات الاستبدادية
who would rehearse, not just the orchestra as a whole, but individuals within it,
لم يكونوا يدربون الاوركسترا كمجموعة، بل كافراد
within an inch of their lives.
قريبين من حياتهم.
But I'm happy to say now that the world has moved on,
و يسعدني ان اقول الان ان ذلك العالم قد تغير
music has moved on with it.
و تغيرت معه الموسيقى ايضا.
We now have a more democratic view and way of making music --
و الان لدينا و جهات نظر اكثر ديمقراطية و لدينا طريقة في التاليف الموسيقي
a two-way street.
تقبل الراي و الراي الاخر.
I, as the conductor, have to come to the rehearsal with a cast-iron sense
و كمايسترو علي ان اتي الى التمرين باحساس قوي ومتماسك كصلابة الحديد
of the outer architecture of that music,
للتصميم الخارجي لتلك الموسيقى
within which there is then immense personal freedom
والتي من خلالها تتألق الحرية الشخصية الهائلة
for the members of the orchestra to shine.
لدى كل من اعضاء الفرقة الموسيقية بابداع
For myself, of course,
و بالنسبة لي طبعا
I have to completely trust my body language.
علي ان اثق تماما بلغة الجسد
That's all I have at the point of sale.
هذا ما علي عمله
It's silent gesture.
انها ايماءة صامتة
I can hardly bark out instructions while we're playing.
لا استطيع ان اعطي التعليمات بصوت عال اثناء العزف
(Music)
موسيقى
Ladies and gentlemen, the Scottish Ensemble.
السيدات و السادة، و الان الى الفرقة الاسكتلندية
(Applause)
تصفيق
So in order for all this to work,
لكي يعمل كل هذا بشكل صحيح
obviously I have got to be in a position of trust.
من الواضح ان علي ان اكون محل ثقة
I have to trust the orchestra,
علي ان اثق بالاوركسترا
and, even more crucially, I have to trust myself.
و اكثر من ذلك كله، على ان اثق بنفسي اولا.
Think about it: when you're in a position of not trusting,
فكر في الامر مليا. تخيل انك في وضع لا توجد فيه ثقة
what do you do?
ماذا ستفعل؟
You overcompensate.
ستكون ردة فعلك مبالغ فيها
And in my game, that means you overgesticulate.
و في مهنتي فذلك يعني المزيد من استخدام حركة اليد
You end up like some kind of rabid windmill.
و سينتهي بك المطاف بان تبدو كطاحونة هوائية سريعة
And the bigger your gesture gets,
و كلما كثرت حركات يدك
the more ill-defined, blurry
كلما بدت التعليمات مشوشة و غير واضحة.
and, frankly, useless it is to the orchestra.
و صراحة ان ذلك يؤثر سلبا على الاوركسترا
You become a figure of fun. There's no trust anymore, only ridicule.
و تصبح محطا للسخرية. فتنعدم الثقة وتحل محلها سخرية محضة.
And I remember at the beginning of my career,
و اتذكر في بداية مشواري الفني،
again and again, on these dismal outings with orchestras,
مرارا وتكرارا, من خلال هذه المنافسات الكئيبة مع فرق الأوركسترا
I would be going completely insane on the podium,
بأني سأجن تماما على المنصة
trying to engender a small scale crescendo really,
كنت أحاول خلق تصعيدا أوالحصول على درجة اعلى في السلم الموسيقي حقيقة
just a little upsurge in volume.
فقط تصاعد صغير بجهارة الصوت.
Bugger me, they wouldn't give it to me.
اللعنة. لم يمنحوني ذلك.
I spent a lot of time in those early years
أمضيت وقتا طويلا في سنواتي الأولى
weeping silently in dressing rooms.
ابكي بصمت في غرفة الملابس
And how futile seemed the words of advice to me
وكم كان يبدو اسداء النصيحة لي عقيما
from great British veteran conductor Sir Colin Davis
من قائد الأوركسترا البريطاني المخضرم سير كولن دافيز
who said, "Conducting, Charles,
الذي قال " قيادة الاوركستر يا تشارلز
is like holding a small bird in your hand.
هي مثل الامساك بعصفور صغير براحة يدك.
If you hold it too tightly, you crush it.
اذا ما أحكمت قبضتك بحزم فسوف تسحقه.
If you hold it too loosely, it flies away."
واذا ما ارخيت قبضتك بشكل كبير. هرب من قبضتك"
I have to say, in those days, I couldn't really even find the bird.
وعلي أن أقول لكم, بانني في تلك الأيام لم أستطع حتى أن أجد عصفورا
Now a fundamental
أما الان فما هو جوهري
and really viscerally important experience for me, in terms of music,
و ما كان عبارة عن تجربة حقا مهمة غريزيا بالنسبة لي, من حيث الموسيقى,
has been my adventures in South Africa,
هو مغامراتي في جنوب افريقيا
the most dizzyingly musical country on the planet in my view,
انها البلد الأكثر اذهالا موسيقيا على وجه الارض من وجهة نظري
but a country which, through its musical culture,
بل وهو البلد الذي من خلال ثقافته الموسيقية
has taught me one fundamental lesson:
علمني درسا جوهريا
that through music making
وهو أنه من خلال تأليف الموسيقى
can come deep levels
يمكن أن تحصل على مستويات عميقة
of fundamental life-giving trust.
من احياء الثقة الجوهرية
Back in 2000, I had the opportunity to go to South Africa
مرة أخرى في عام 2000، أتيحت لي الفرصة للذهاب الى جنوب افريقيا
to form a new opera company.
لتأسيس شركة جديدة للأوبرا
So I went out there, and I auditioned,
حتى انني ذهبت الى هناك، وقمت باجراء تجربة أداء ،
mainly in rural township locations, right around the country.
وبشكل اساسي في المناطق الريفية. وايضا في جميع أنحاء البلاد.
I heard about 2,000 singers
قمت بسماع حوالي الفي مطرب
and pulled together a company
و انشأنا معا شركة
of 40 of the most jaw-droppingly amazing young performers,
حوالي اربعين من اكثر الفنانين اذهالا ممن تفغر لهم الافواه
the majority of whom were black,
ومعظمهم كانوا من السود
but there were a handful of white performers.
ولكن كان يوجد حفنة من الفنانين البيض.
Now it emerged early on in the first rehearsal period
وظهر في وقت مبكر من فترة تجارب الاداء
that one of those white performers
بأن احد هؤلاء الفنانين البيض
had, in his previous incarnation,
في منصبه السابق
been a member of the South African police force.
كان عضوا في قوى شرطة جنوب افريقيا
And in the last years of the old regime,
وفي السنوات الأخيرة من النظام القديم ،
he would routinely be detailed to go into the township
كان بشكل روتيني مفرزا للذهاب الى البلدة
to aggress the community.
ليرهب الناس
Now you can imagine what this knowledge did to the temperature in the room,
ويمكنكم الان ان تتخيلوا كيف أن معرفة ذلك زادت التوتر والضغط في المحيط
the general atmosphere.
والجو العام
Let's be under no illusions.
دعونا نزيل الاوهام وننظر للحقيقة
In South Africa, the relationship most devoid of trust
في جنوب أفريقيا, ان اكثر العلاقات المتزعزعة هي الثقة
is that between a white policeman
بين شرطي ابيض
and the black community.
و المجتمع الاسود
So how do we recover from that, ladies and gentlemen?
فكيف يمكننا اصلاح ذلك سيداتي سادتي؟
Simply through singing.
بكل بساطة من خلال الغناء
We sang, we sang,
غنينا وغنينا
we sang,
وغنينا
and amazingly new trust grew,
فنما نوع جديد من الثقة بشكل مدهش
and indeed friendship blossomed.
و فعلا ازهرت نوعا جديدا من الصداقة
And that showed me such a fundamental truth,
وهذا ما وضح لي حقيقة جوهرية
that music making and other forms of creativity
بأن تأليف الموسيقى وأنواع أخرى مختلفة من الأبداع
can so often go to places
يمكنها في كثير من الأحيان أن تصل وبسهولة
where mere words cannot.
الى حيث لا يمكن للكلمات المجردة أن تصل
So we got some shows off the ground. We started touring them internationally.
بدأنا ببعض العروض. ومن ثم بدأنا بجولة على الصعيد الدولي.
One of them was "Carmen."
كانت احدى هذه العروض "كارمن"
We then thought we'd make a movie of "Carmen,"
وبعدها فكرنا بصناعة فلم بعنوان "كارمن"
which we recorded and shot outside on location
والذي قمنا بتسجيله وتصويره في احد المواقع
in the township outside Cape Town called Khayelitsha.
في احد البلدات خارج كيب تاون وتدعى خيليتشا
The piece was sung entirely in Xhosa,
وقد تم غناء القطعة الموسيقية كاملة بالأكسوزا
which is a beautifully musical language, if you don't know it.
والتي هي احد اللغات الموسيقية الجميلة اذا كنتم لا تعرفون
It's called "U-Carmen e-Khayelitsha" --
وتدعى " يو كارمن ايخيليتشا"
literally "Carmen of Khayelitsha."
حرفيا"" كارمن خيليلتشا"
I want to play you a tiny clip of it now
سأعرض لكم مقطعا صغيرا منها الان
for no other reason than to give you proof positive
ليس لاي سبب اخر غير اعطائكم دليلا ايجابيا
that there is nothing tiny about South African music making.
بأنه لا يوجد شيء ضئيل في تأليف الموسيقا في جنوب افريقيا
(Music)
"موسيقا"
(Applause)
"تصفيق"
Something which I find utterly enchanting
سبب اخر يجعلني أرى سحرا مطلقا
about South African music making
في عالم تأليف الموسيقا في جنوب افريقيا
is that it's so free.
هي أنها منطلقة وحرة بشكل كبير
South Africans just make music really freely.
اهالي جنوب افريقيا يؤلفون الموسيقا بحرية كاملة على الأطلاق
And I think, in no small way,
واعتقد بأن ذلك يعود وبشكل أساسي
that's due to one fundamental fact:
الى حقيقة جوهرية
they're not bound to a system of notation.
وهي أنهم ليسوا ملزمين بنظام منهجي
They don't read music.
هم لا يدرسون الموسيقى
They trust their ears.
بل فقط يثقون بمسامعهم
You can teach a bunch of South Africans a tune in about five seconds flat.
يمكنك تعليم مجموعة من الأفارقة لحنا ما بغضون خمس ثوان فقط
And then, as if by magic,
ومن ثم ، كما لو كان بفعل السحر ،
they will spontaneously improvise a load of harmony around that tune
يرتجلون بصورة تلقائية شحنة من التناغم لذلك اللحن
because they can.
فقط لأنهم قادرون على ذلك
Now those of us that live in the West, if I can use that term,
أما أولئك الذين يعيشون في الغرب منا، اذا كان يمكنني استخدام هذا المصطلح ،
I think have a much more hidebound attitude or sense of music --
اعتقد بأن لديهم حسا اكثر جمودا من حيث الموسيقا بكثير
that somehow it's all about skill and systems.
بطريقة أو بأخرى كل شيء يعتمد على المهارات والانظمة.
Therefore it's the exclusive preserve
لذلك فهي حكر خاص
of an elite, talented body.
بنخبة من الموهوبين.
And yet, ladies and gentlemen, every single one of us on this planet
ومع ذلك ، أيها السيدات والسادة ، كل واحد منا على هذا الكوكب
probably engages with music on a daily basis.
ربما يمارس ويشارك بالموسيقا بشكل يومي
And if I can broaden this out for a second,
واذا امكنني توسيع هذا النطاق لثانية
I'm willing to bet that every single one of you sitting in this room
وأنا على استعداد للمراهنة بأن كل واحد منكم يجلس في هذه الغرفة
would be happy to speak with acuity, with total confidence,
سيكون سعيدا للتحدث ببراعة وبثقة تامة،
about movies, probably about literature.
عن الأفلام وحتى عن الأدب
But how many of you would be able to make a confident assertion
ولكن كم منكم سيكون قادرا على طرح مزاعم واثقة
about a piece of classical music?
حول قطعة من الموسيقا الكلاسيكية؟
Why is this?
ما سبب ذلك؟
And what I'm going to say to you now
وما اردت قوله لكم الان
is I'm just urging you to get over
هو انني أحثكم فقط على تجاوز
this supreme lack of self-confidence,
هذا النقص الكبير بالثقة بالنفس
to take the plunge, to believe that you can trust your ears,
لأخذ زمام المبادرة، والايمان بأنه يمكنكم الوثوق بآذانكم،
you can hear some of the fundamental muscle tissue,
يمكنك الاستماع لبعض الألياف العضلية الأساسية
fiber, DNA,
والأنسجة ، والحمض النووي
what makes a great piece of music great.
ما يجعل قطعة كبيرة من الموسيقى الرائعة
I've got a little experiment I want to try with you.
حصلت على قليل من الخبرة التي اريد ان اجربها معكم
Did you know
هل تعلمون
that TED is a tune?
بان تيد هي لحن؟
A very simple tune based on three notes -- T, E, D.
لحن بسيط جدا يعتمد على ثلاث نوتات تي , اي , دي
Now hang on a minute.
والان انتظروا لحظة
I know you're going to say to me, "T doesn't exist in music."
اعلم بأنكم ستقولون لي بأن تي لا توجد في السلم الموسيقي
Well ladies and gentlemen, there's a time-honored system,
حسنا سيداتي وسادتي, هناك نظام عريق،
which composers have been using for hundreds of years,
والذي كان يستخدمه الملحنون لمئات السنين
which proves actually that it does.
والذي يثبت بأن تي كانت موجودة حقا في السلم الموسيقي
If I sing you a musical scale: A, B, C, D, E, F, G --
اذا غنيت لكم سلما موسيقيا " اي بي سي دي اي اف جي
and I just carry on with the next set of letters in the alphabet, same scale:
وتابعت بالمجموعة الباقية لأحرف الابجدية بنفس السلم
H, I, J, K, L, M, N,
اتش ,اي ,جي, كي, ال, ام, ان
O, P, Q, R, S, T -- there you go.
او , بي , كيو, ار, اس , تي ها هي ذي
T, see it's the same as F in music.
ولذلك فان تي هي نفس اف في السلم الموسيقي
So T is F.
ولذلك فان تي هي اف
So T, E, D is the same as F, E, D.
ولذا فان تي , اي , دي هي نفس في , اي , دي
Now that piece of music that we played at the start of this session
ولذلك فان تلك القطعة الموسيقية التي عزفناها في هذه الجلسة
had enshrined in its heart
كرست في قلبها
the theme, which is TED.
الموضوع الذي هو تيد
Have a listen.
استمعوا اليها
(Music)
"موسيقا"
Do you hear it?
هل سمعتم هذا؟
Or do I smell some doubt in the room?
ام انني اشتم رائحة الشك في ارجاء الغرفة؟
Okay, we'll play it for you again now,
حسنا , سنعزفها لكم مرة اخرى الان
and we're going to highlight, we're going to poke out the T, E, D.
سوف نسلط الضوء ونظهر الـ تي , اي , دي.
If you'll pardon the expression.
واعذرني لهذا التعبير
(Music)
"موسيقا"
Oh my goodness me, there it was loud and clear, surely.
يا الهي ، ها هي كانت هناك بصوت عال وواضح، وبالتأكيد
I think we should make this even more explicit.
اعتقد بانه يجب ان نجعلها حتى اكثر وضوحا
Ladies and gentlemen, it's nearly time for tea.
سيداتي سادتي, قد اقترب وقت الشاي
Would you reckon you need to sing for your tea, I think?
هل تعتقدون بانكم بحاجة لان اغني لكم من اجل الشاي , كما أظن؟
I think we need to sing for our tea.
اعتقد بأنه علينا ان نغني من اجل الشاي
We're going to sing those three wonderful notes: T, E, D.
سوف نغني هذي النوتات الرائعة الثلاثة تي , اي , دي
Will you have a go for me?
هل يمكنكم غناءها من أجلي؟
Audience: T, E, D.
الجمهور " تي , اي , دي"
Charles Hazlewood: Yeah, you sound a bit more like cows really than human beings.
اجل تبدون نوعا ما كقطيع من الابقار اكثر من ان تكونوا بشرا
Shall we try that one again?
هل يمكننا المحاولة مرة أخرى؟
And look, if you're adventurous, you go up the octave.
وانظروا, اذا كنتم تحبون المغامرة, يمكنكم رفع طبقتكم الصوتية
T, E, D.
تي , اي , دي
Audience: T, E, D.
الجمهور : تي , اي , دي
CH: Once more with vim. (Audience: T, E, D.)
مرة أخرى بهمة عاليه ( الجمهور: تي , اي , دي
There I am like a bloody windmill again, you see.
ها أنا ذا مثل طاحونة مجنونة مرة أخرى كما ترون
Now we're going to put that in the context of the music.
الان علينا أن نضع ذلك في سياق الموسيقى
The music will start, and then at a signal from me, you will sing that.
ستبدأ الموسيقى وباشارة مني ستبدأون انتم بالغناء
(Music)
"موسيقا"
One more time,
مرة أخرى
with feeling, ladies and gentlemen.
باحساس , سيداتي سادتي
You won't make the key otherwise.
والا فلن تكونوا قادرين على الوصول للمفتاح
Well done, ladies and gentlemen.
أحسنتم سيداتي سادتي
It wasn't a bad debut for the TED choir,
لم يكن ذلك سيئا في أول ظهور لكم جوقة تيد
not a bad debut at all.
ليست بداية سيئة على الاطلاق
Now there's a project that I'm initiating at the moment
هناك مشروع ساقوم بالشروع به في هذه اللحظة
that I'm very excited about and wanted to share with you,
وانا متحمس جدا لاجله وأود أن اشاطركم اياه
because it is all about changing perceptions,
لان كل ما في الامر هوعن تغيير المفاهيم
and, indeed, building a new level of trust.
و بناء مستوى جديد من الثقة
The youngest of my children was born with cerebral palsy,
ولد أصغر ابنائي مصابا بشلل دماغي
which as you can imagine,
والذي كما يمكنكم أن تتخيلوا
if you don't have an experience of it yourself,
حتى وان لم يكن لديكم تجربة شخصية
is quite a big thing to take on board.
هو عبئ ثقيل يمكنك أن تحمله على عاتقك
But the gift that my gorgeous daughter has given me,
ولكن الهبة التي منحتني اياها ابنتي الرائعة
aside from her very existence,
عدا عن وجودها في حياتي
is that it's opened my eyes to a whole stretch of the community
هي انها فتحتت عيناي على مجتمع ممتد بالكامل
that was hitherto hidden,
ومع ذلك مختفي
the community of disabled people.
مجتمع الناس ذوي الاحتياجات الخاصة
And I found myself looking at the Paralympics and thinking how incredible
ووجدت نفسي اتابع العاب القوى وافكر كم هو امر لا يصدق
how technology's been harnessed to prove beyond doubt
كيف تم تسخير التكنولوجيا لتثبت بالدليل القاطع
that disability is no barrier
بأن العجز ليس عائقا
to the highest levels of sporting achievement.
أعلى مستويات الانجازات الرياضية
Of course there's a grimmer side to that truth,
بالطبع هناك جانب مظلم لتلك الحقيقة
which is that it's actually taken decades for the world at large
وهو أن تتخذ في الواقع منذ عقود للعالم بأسره
to come to a position of trust,
وان تصل الى موضع من الثقة
to really believe that disability and sports can go together
بأن تؤمن حقا بأن العجز والرياضة يسيران جنبا الى جنب
in a convincing and interesting fashion.
بطريقة عصرية مقنعة ومثيرة للاهتمام
So I find myself asking:
لذلك اجد نفسي اتساءل
where is music in all of this?
اين هي الموسيقا من كل هذا؟
You can't tell me that there aren't millions of disabled people,
لا يمكنك أن تقول لي بأنه ليس هناك الملايين من الأشخاص المعوقين،
in the U.K. alone,
في المملكة المتحدة وحدها
with massive musical potential.
ممن يمتلكون امكانات موسيقية ضخمة
So I decided to create a platform for that potential.
لذا قررت ان ابتكر منهاج عمل يتناسب مع تلك الامكانيات
It's going to be Britain's first ever
ستكون الاولى من نوعها على الاطلاق في بريطانيا
national disabled orchestra.
الاوركسترا العالمية للمعوقين
It's called Paraorchestra.
وسأدعوها بالبارااوركسترا
I'm going to show you a clip now
سأعرض لكم مقطعا مصورا الان
of the very first improvisation session that we had.
من أول دورة ارتجالية قمنا بها على الاطلاق
It was a really extraordinary moment.
كانت لحظة استثنائية حقا.
Just me and four astonishingly gifted disabled musicians.
فقط أنا واربع من الموسيقين المعوقين الموهوبين بشكل استثنائي
Normally when you improvise --
عادة عندما يطلب منك الارتجال
and I do it all the time around the world --
وانا أقوم بالارتجال طوال الوقت حول العالم
there's this initial period of horror,
يوجد هناك تلك الفترة المبدئية من الرهبة
like everyone's too frightened to throw the hat into the ring,
ومثل الجميع خائفا جدا من رمي القبعة في الحلبة،
an awful pregnant silence.
بصمت واعد ومروع
Then suddenly, as if by magic, bang! We're all in there
ثم فجأة,كما لو كان بفعل السحر, كنا كلنا هناك
and it's complete bedlam. You can't hear anything.
كان هناك هرج ومرج صاخب. لا يمكنك سماع اي شيء
No one's listening. No one's trusting.
لا أحد يصغي . ولا أحد يتحلى بالثقة
No one's responding to each other.
ولا أحد يتجاوب مع الاخر
Now in this room with these four disabled musicians,
الان في هذه الغرفة ومع هؤلاء الموسيقين الاربعة من ذوي الاحتياجات الخاصة
within five minutes
و بغضون خمس دقائق
a rapt listening, a rapt response
استماع طرب ورد جذل
and some really insanely beautiful music.
وبعض الموسيقى الجميلة حقا بجنون.
(Video) (Music)
(فيديو ) (موسيقا)
Nicholas:: My name's Nicholas McCarthy.
نيكولاس :اسمي نيكولاس ماكارثي
I'm 22, and I'm a left-handed pianist.
وانا في الـ 22, وانا عازف بيانو أعسر
And I was born without my left hand -- right hand.
وقد ولدت بدون يدي اليسرى .. اقصد يدي اليمنى
Can I do that one again?
هل يمكنني عزف ذلك مرة أخرى؟
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Lyn: When I'm making music,
لين: عندما أعزف الموسيقى
I feel like a pilot in the cockpit flying an airplane.
أشعر بأنني كابتن في قمرة القيادة لأحلق بطائرة
I become alive.
أشعر بأنني على قيد الحياة
(Music)
(موسيقا)
Clarence: I would rather be able to play an instrument again
كلارينس: أفضل ان اعزف على الة موسيقية
than walk.
اكثر من ان استعيد القدرة على المشي
There's so much joy and things
يوجد الكثير من المتعة والاشياء
I could get from playing an instrument and performing.
التي يمكن ان احصل عليها من العزف على الة موسيقية والاداء
It's removed some of my paralysis.
لقد ازالت بعضا من اعاقتي
(Music)
(موسيقا)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
CH: I only wish that some of those musicians were here with us today,
كنت اتمنى لو ان بعضا من هؤلاء الموسيقين كانوا معنا هنا اليوم
so you could see at firsthand how utterly extraordinary they are.
حتى تستطيعوا ان تروا بأنفسكم كم هم حقا مميزين
Paraorchestra is the name of that project.
الباراكيسترا هو اسم ذلك المشروع
If any of you thinks you want to help me in any way
ان اراد أي منكم ان يساعدني بأية طريقة
to achieve what is a fairly impossible and implausible dream still at this point,
لتحقيق هذا الحلم الذي ما زال حتى هذه اللحظة مستحيلا نوعا ما وغير معقول
please let me know.
ارجو اعلامي
Now my parting shot
والان محطتي الوداعية
comes courtesy of the great Joseph Haydn,
هي تقدمة لجوزيف هايدن العظيم
wonderful Austrian composer in the second half of the 18th century --
الملحن النمساوي الرائع في النصف الثاني من القرن الثامن عشر
spent the bulk of his life
والذي أمضى معظم حياته
in the employ of Prince Nikolaus Esterhazy, along with his orchestra.
في خدمة الأمير نيكولاس استرازي بمرافقة الاوركسترا الخاصة به
Now this prince loved his music,
طبعا هذا الامير أحب موسيقاه
but he also loved the country castle that he tended to reside in most of the time,
ولكنه أيضا أحب قصر البلد الذي يميل للاقامة فيه معظم الوقت
which is just on the Austro-Hungarian border,
والذي هو فقط مكان على حدود اوسترو هنغاريا
a place called Esterhazy --
مكانا يدعى استرازي
a long way from the big city of Vienna.
بعيدا عن المدينة البعيدة في فيينا
Now one day in 1772,
وفي احدى الايام من عام 1772
the prince decreed that the musicians' families,
أصدر الأمير مرسوما يقضي بأن أسر الموسيقين
the orchestral musicians' families,
عائلات موسيقيي الأوركسترا
were no longer welcome in the castle.
لم يعد مرحب بهم في القصر
They weren't allowed to stay there anymore; they had to be returned to Vienna --
ولم يسمح لهم بالبقاء هناك بعد ذلك، بل كان لا بد لهم من العودة الى فيينا --
as I say, an unfeasibly long way away in those days.
وكما كنت أقول فالطريق كان بعيدا وغير ممكن في تلك الايام
You can imagine, the musicians were disconsolate.
ويمكنكم تخيل كم كان الموسيقين مفطوري القلب
Haydn remonstrated with the prince, but to no avail.
اعترض هيدن على الأمير ولكن من دون جدوى
So given the prince loved his music,
وبما أن الامير كان يحب موسيقاه
Haydn thought he'd write a symphony to make the point.
ففكر بتأليف سمفونية لايصال فكرته
And we're going to play just the very tail end of this symphony now.
وسوف نعزف لكم اخر جزء من السمفونية الان
And you'll see the orchestra in a kind of sullen revolt.
وسترون أفراد الأوركسترا متجهمون بنوع من التمرد
I'm pleased to say, the prince did take the tip
ويسعدني أن أخبركم بأن الأمير اخذ بالنصيحة
from the orchestral performance,
من أداء الأوركسترا
and the musicians were reunited with their families.
وبعدها جمع شمل الموسيقين مع عائلاتهم
But I think it sums up my talk rather well, this,
و اعتقد بانها تلخص كلامي بشكل واضح
that where there is trust,
بأنه حيثما وجدت الثقة
there is music -- by extension life.
توجد الموسيقى وكامتداد لها في الحياة
Where there is no trust,
حيث تنعدم ثقة
the music quite simply withers away.
تذبل الموسيقى بشكل كبير
(Music)
موسيقى
(Applause)
تصفيق